Ei Pa Pa Pe-Than

eipa [at] cmu [dot] edu | https://eipapa.github.io/ | Google Scholar | Research Gate | @eipa01 | GitHub

Research Interests and Approach

My research interests span computer-supported cooperative work (CSCW), science and technologies studies (STS), and critical human-computer interaction (HCI), and especially how to develop, maintain, and evolve a decentralized distributed software system that builds on a novel and sophisticated coordination architecture that addresses reinterpretability, resilience, and scalability.

I use case study research approach to address complex socio-technical questions, which includes ethnography (interviews and non-participant observations), archival analysis, quantitative collection of log and trace data with Python, SQL, and R, and a combination of all of these methods (mixed-methods) as relevant and appropriate.

Education

Carnegie Mellon V	University Pittsburgh, PA, USA
Jun 2020 (expected)	Postdoctoral Researcher Advisor: James Herbsleb, Institute for Software Research, School of Computer Science Topic: Large-scale coordination in time-bounded events (hackathons, datathons, etc.) for science, innovation, learning, and community building, and open-text projects on GitHub
Nanyang Technol	ogical University Singapore, Singapore
Apr 2016	Doctor of Philosophy in Information Systems Advisor: Dion Hoe-Lian Goh and Chei Sian Lee, Wee Kim Wee School of Communication and Information Thesis: Investigating user-centered human computation games: The role of perceived enjoyment and its antecedents
Jun 2009	Master of Science in Information Systems
University of Con	nputer Studies Yangon, Myanmar
Jun 2005	Bachelor of Science (Hons.) in Computer Science

Employment

Carnegie Mellon University	Pittsburgh, PA, USA
June 2017–present	Postdoctoral Researcher Advisor: James Herbsleb, Institute for Software Research, School of Computer Science Topic: Coordination in time-bounded events (hackathons, datathons, etc.) for science, innovation, learning, and community building, and collaborative writing on GitHub
Nanyang Technological Univ	versity Singapore, Singapore
Nov 2015–Nov 2016	Research Associate and Part-time Lecturer
NCS	Singapore, Singapore
Jun 2009–Jul 2010	Application Consultant (Software Developer)
University of Computer Stud	ies Yangon, Myanmar
2005–2007	Tutor

Publications

Referred Journal Publications

- 1. **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, Nolte, A., Filippova, A., Bird, C., Scallen, S., and Herbsleb, J.D. "Corporate Hackathons, How and Why? A Multiple Case Study of Motivation, Project Proposal and Selection, Goal Setting, Coordination, and Project Continuation." [Revisions submitted to Human-Computer Interaction Journal]
- 2. **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, Dabbish, L., and Herbsleb, J.D. "Collaborative Writing at Scale: Investigation of Pull-Based Model on GitHub." [Under the review of CSCW 2020]
- 3. Nolte, A., **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, Filippova, A., Bird, C., Scallen, S., and Herbsleb, J.D. (2018). "You Hacked and Now What?: Exploring Outcomes of a Corporate Hackathon." In Proceedings of the ACM on Human Computer Interaction, 2 (CSCW'18), Article 129, 23 pages. https://doi.org/10.1145/3274398
- 4. **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, Nolte, A., Filippova, A., Bird, C., Scallen, S., and Herbsleb, J.D. (2018). "Designing Corporate Hackathons with a Purpose." IEEE Software, 36 (1), 15-22. https://doi.org/10.1002/asi.23863

Referred Conference Publications

1. **Pe-Than, E.P.P.** and Herbsleb, J.D. (2019). "Understanding Hackathons for Science: Collaboration, Affordances, and Outcomes." In Taylor N., Christian-Lamb C., Martin M., Nardi B. (eds) Information in Contemporary Society, iConference'19. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, vol 11420 (iConference'19), pp. 27-37. Springer, Cham. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-15742-5 3

Referred Short Publications

 Pe-Than, E.P.P., Dabbish, L., and Herbsleb, J.D. (2018). "Collaborative Writing on GitHub: A Case Study of a Book Project." In Companion of the 2018 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW'18), pp. 305-308. https://doi.org/10.1145/3272973.3274083

Referred Workshop Publications

Pe-Than, E.P.P., Herbsleb, J.D., Nolte, A., Gerber, E., Fiore-Gartland, B., Chapman, B., Moser, A., and Wilkins-Diehr, N. (2018). "The 2nd Workshop on Hacking and Making at Time-Bounded Events: Current Trends and Next Steps in Research and Event Design." In Extended Abstracts of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI EA'18), paper W35, 8 pages. https://doi.org/10.1145/3170427.3170615

Technical Reports

1. **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, and Nolte, A. (2018). "The 2nd Workshop on Hacking and Making at Time-Bounded Events." Technical Report CMU-ISR-18-109, Carnegie Mellon University. http://eipapa.github.io/files/ISR-techreport-2018.pdf

Posters

- 1. **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, Dabbish, L., and Herbsleb, J.D. (2019). "Collaborative Writing at Scale: A Case Study of Two Open-Text Projects Done on GitHub." Paper presented at The Future of Work, Human Computer Interaction Consortium (HCIC'19). http://eipapa.github.io/files/HCIC-poster-2019.pdf
- 2. **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, Dabbish, L., and Herbsleb, J.D. (2019). "Collaborative Writing at Scale: A Case Study of Two Open-Text Projects Done on GitHub." Poster presented at the 7th ACM Conference on Collective Intelligence 2019 (CI'19). https://ci.acm.org/2019/assets/proceedings/CI 2019 paper 65.pdf https://eipapa.github.io/files/CI-poster-2019.pdf
- 3. **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, Momcheva, I., Tolleud, E., and Herbsleb, J.D. (2019). "Hackathons for Science, How and Why?" Poster presented at the 233rd Meeting of the American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #233, id.459.11. https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019AAS...23345911P/abstract

- 4. Powell, J., Hayden, L., Nolte, A., Herbsleb, J.D., **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, Wong, M., Kalyanam, R., Ellet, K., Pamidighantam, S., Traxler, K., and Cannon, A. (2018). "An Analysis of the PEARC 2018 Science Gateways Community Institute Hackathon: Lessons Learned." Poster presented at Gateways 2018 organized by the Science Gateways Community Institute (SGCI). https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.7070309.v2
- 5. **Pe-Than, E.P.P.**, Nolte, A., Filippova, A., Bird, C., Scallen, S. and Herbsleb, J.D. (2018). "An Empirical Study of Team Familiarity, Goal Setting, and Process in Time-Bounded Events." Poster presented at the 13th Annual Interdisciplinary Network for Group Research Conference (INGRoup'18).

Teaching

Nanyang Technological University, Singapore

Instructor

CI6221	Information Visualization (cross-listed, graduate)	Aug 2016
CI6228	Managing Information Systems (graduate)	Jan 2016
IN9008	Digital Social Games for Organizations (undergraduate)	Jan 2015

Teaching Assistant

IN9006	Social Computing and Applications (graduate)	Jan 2014
CS2008	Fundamentals of Research (undergraduate)	Aug 2013
CI6208	Research Methods and Data Analysis for Information Professionals (graduate)	Jan 2013
CI6222	Mobile & Ubiquitous Applications (graduate)	Aug 2012

University of Computer Studies, Yangon

Tutor	Fundamentals of Data Structures (undergraduate)	2006–2007
	Operating Systems (undergraduate)	2006-2007

Professional Services

Reviewing

2020	ECIS: European Conference on Information Systems iConference
2019	CSCW: ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work ECIS: European Conference on Information Systems iConference

2018	CHI: ACM Conference on Computer-Human Interaction ECIS: European Conference on Information Systems iConference
2017	CHI: ACM Conference on Computer-Human Interaction Journal of Information Science Theory and Practice
2016	Cyberpsychology, Behavior, and Social Networking Aslib Journal of Information Management
2015	ECIS: European Conference on Information Systems

Organizing

2019	World of Code (WoC) Hackathon, Carnegie Mellon University
2018	Science Gateways Hackathon by the Science Gateways Community Institute (SGCI), collocated with PEARC18 Conference, Wyndham Grand Pittsburgh
2018	The 2nd Workshop on Hacking and Making at Time-Bounded Events: Current Trends and Next Steps in Research and Event Design, ACM CHI'18 conference, Montreal, Canada

Volunteering

2020	Member of the SCS Voting Study Committee
2020	Withhelf of the Ses voting Study Committee
2016	The 66th Annual Conference of the International Communication Association (ICA)
2011–2013	Graduate Admission Exercise, Wee Kim Wee School of Communication and Information
2011	International Conference on Social Informatics (SocInfo2011)

Professional Associations

ACM ACM SIGCHI	Association for Computing Machinery Special Interest Group on Computer–Human Interaction
ACM SIGSOFT ASIS&T	Special Interest Group on Software Engineering Association for Information Science & Technology

References

James Herbsleb

Professor of Computer Science Institute for Software Research School of Computer Science Carnegie Mellon University

Alexander Nolte

Lecturer (Assistant Professor), Institute of Computer Science, University of Tartu Adjunct Assistant Professor, Institute for Software Research, Carnegie Mellon University